本章最后一节，我想为大家展示一个通用攻击
In the last segment in this module, I
wanna show you a general attack that
它影响了许多MAC算法的实现
affects many implementations of MAC
algorithms. And there's a nice lesson to
这种攻击给了我们很好的教训。我们看一个
be learned from an attack like this. So
let's look at a particular implementation
特别的HMAC验证的实现。这个实现正好来自Keyczar库
of HMAC verification. This happens to be
an implementation from the Keyczar library,
它是用Python写的。这是用于验证HMAC标签的代码
that happens to be written in Python. So
here's the code that's used to verify a
这个代码实际上被简化了
tag generated by HMAC. This code is
actually simplified. I just wanted to
我只想尽量简化它，以直击要点
kinda simplify it as much as I can to get
the point across. So basically, what the
输入为密钥、信息和标签。我们验证的方法是
inputs are, the key, the message, and the
tag bytes. The way we verify it is, we
重新计算信息的HMAC，然后比较得到的16字节
re-compute the HMAC on the message and
then we compare say the resulting sixteen
与实际给的签名16字节。这看上去很好
bytes, to the actual given signature
bytes. So this looks perfectly fine.
事实上，任何人可以想到这样实现它。
也已经有很多人像这样实现了
In fact, anyone might implement it like this.
And, in fact, many people have implemented
问题是，如果你看这里的比较是如何实现的
it like this. The problem is, that if you
look at how the comparison is done, the
你可能觉得，比较应该是逐字节地进行
comparison, as you might expect, is done
byte by byte. There's a loop inside of the
Python翻译器里有一个循环遍历所有16个字节
Python interpreter that loops over all
sixteen bytes. And it so happens that the
第一次它发现不相等的话，循环终止
first time it finds an inequality, the
loop terminates and says the strings are
说两字符串不相等。当找到第一个不相等的字节
就退出比较的这一事实
not equal. And the fact that the
comparator exits when the first inequality
造成了针对该密码库的一个严重的计时攻击
is found introduces a significant timing
attack on this library. So let me show you
我来告诉大家如何攻击。设想你是攻击者，你有信息m
how one might attack it. So imagine you're
the attacker, and you have the message m,
你想获得m的一个有效标签。现在，你的目标是攻击一个服务器
for which you want to obtain a valid tag.
Now, your goal is to attack a server that
这个服务器存放着HMAC的密钥。这个服务器开放了一个接口
has an HMAC secret key stored in it. And
the server exposes an interface that
这个接口接收信息与MAC，检查这个MAC是否有效
basically takes message MAC pairs. Checks
that the MAC is valid, if the MAC is valid
如果MAC有效，服务器用这个信息进行操作；
如果MAC无效，服务器拒绝
it does something with the message. And if
the MAC is not valid, it says reject.
退回到信息发送方，或拒绝这条信息
Okay, so it's back to the originator or
the message rejects. So now this attacker
现在这个攻击者有机会提交大量信息
has an opportunity to basically submit
lots of message it appears and see if it
看看能不能推出特定的攻击信息的标签
can deduce the tags of the particular
message for which it once attacked. Here's
我们可以使用根据上一页的被破解的实现来做
how we might use the broken implementation
from the previous slide to do just that.
攻击者提交许多信息，询问信息的标签
So what the attacker is gonna do is to
submit many message tag queries, where the
而信息始终是一样的，但对于标签来说
message is always the same. But with a
tag, he's gonna experiment with lots and
攻击者尝试很多不同的标签。在第一个询问里
lots and lots of different tags. So in the
first query, what he's gonna do is just
攻击者提交目标信息和一个随机标签
submit a random tag along with the target
message. And he's gonna measure how long
然后攻击者测量服务器的反应时间。他提交的下一个询问
the server took to respond. The next query
that he's gonna submit, is he's gonna try
将尝试标签的第一字节的所有256种情况。
我来解释一下我的意思
all possible first bytes for the tags. Let
me explain what I mean by that. So the
而标签中剩下的字节是任意选取的
remaining bytes of the tags that he
submits are just arbitrary, doesn't really
它们是什么并不重要。但对于第一个字节
matter what they are. But for the first
byte, what he'll do is he'll submit a tag
攻击者会提交一个以0字节开头的标签，
然后他观察服务器是否比之前
starting with a byte zero. And then he's
gonna see whether the server took a little
花稍微长一点的时间来验证标签。
如果服务器花了与第一步严格相同的时间
bit longer to verify the tag than before.
If the server took exactly the same amount
来验证这个标签，那么攻击者会再次尝试
of time to verify the tag as in step one,
then he's gonna try again, this time with
这次以字节1开头。如果服务器依然反应迅速
bytes at one. If still the server
responded very quickly, he's going to try
攻击者会尝试以字节2开头。如果服务器还是反应迅速
with byte sets of two. If the server
responded quickly then he's going to try
攻击者会尝试以字节3开头，等等。。直到，比如说
with byte sets of three, and so on until
finally, let's say, when the byte sets of
以3开头时，服务器花了稍微长一点的时间给出反应
three the server takes a little bit longer
to respond. What that means is actually
就意味着当服务器比较正确的MAC和攻击者提交的MAC时
when it did the comparison between the
correct MAC and the MAC submitted by the
在这个字节上，两个MAC是一样的，而不一样的是第二个字节
attacker. The two matched on this byte,
and the rejection happened on the second
现在攻击者知道标签的第一个字节是3了
bytes. Aha. So now the attacker knows that
the first byte of the tag is set to three
现在他可以对第二个字节实施一模一样的攻击
and now he can mount exactly the same
attack on the second byte. So here. It's
提交这个标签。第二个字节，我用不同颜色
going to submit the tag. And the second,
back here, let me use a different color. So
攻击者会提交一个标签，标签的第二个字节是0
it's gonna submit a tag when the second
byte is set to zero. And it's gonna
攻击者将测量这是否会花比第二步更长的时间
measure whether this took a little bit
longer than in step two. If not, he's
如果不是，他将把第二个字节换成1
gonna change this to be set to one, and
he's gonna measure if the server's
攻击者将测量服务器的反应时间，是否比之前长
response time is a little longer than
before. Eventually, let's say when he sets
最终，攻击者会把第二个字节设为，不太清楚，
比如说是53吧，突然间
this to, I don't know. When the byte is
set to, to 53, say, all of a sudden, the
服务器反应的时间稍微长一点了
server takes a little bit longer to
respond. Which means that now, the
这意味着比较器在前两个字节上是匹配的。
现在攻击者学习到了
comparator matched on the first two bytes.
And now the attacker learned that the
MAC的前两个字节分别是3和53。现在攻击者可以继续
first two bytes of the MAC are three and
53. And now he can move on and do the
对第三个字节进行同样的攻击，接着第4个字节，等等
exact same thing on the third byte and
then on the fourth byte and so on and so
最终，服务器说，好，我接受
forth. Until finally, the server says,
yes, I accept. You actually gave me the
你已经给我正确的MAC了。然后我们继续
在这个假信息上做手脚，攻击我们的服务器
right MAC. And then we'll go ahead and act
on this bogus message. That, attack our
那么这是一个漂亮的攻击实例，如何使用计时攻击
supply. So this is a beautiful example of
how a timing attack can reveal the value
来找到MAC值，正确的MAC。一字节、一字节地
of a MAC, the correct value of the MAC.
Kind of byte by byte, until eventually,
知道攻击者获得标签中所有正确的字节
the attacker obtains all the correct bytes
of the tag, and then he's able to fool the
然后他就可以欺骗服务器接收信息的标签。
我喜欢讲这个例子的原因是
server into accepting this message tag
pair. The reason I like this example is
这是一个非常合理的实现MAC验证的程序
this is a perfectly reasonable way of
implementing a MAC verification routine.
如果你这样实现，它会被完全破解的，那我们怎么办？
And yet, if you write it this way, it will
be completely broken. So what do we do? So
让我们告诉大家两种防御方法，第一种是重新用Python写
let me show you two defenses, the first
defense, I'll write it in again in python
事实上Keyczar严格地实现了这种防御
is, is as follows. In fact the Keyczar
library exactly implemented this defense.
这份代码已经出现在更新版本的库中了
This code is actually taken out of the
updated version of the library. The first
首先我们看攻击者提交的签名的字节数是否正确
thing we do is we test if the signature
bytes submitted by the attacker are of the
对于HMAC来说是96位或128位
correct length, say for HMAC this would
be say, you know 96 bits or 128 bits, and
如果不是，我们就不承认这是个有效的MAC。
现在，如果签名确实有正确的长度
if not we reject that as an invalid MAC.
But now, if the signature bytes really do
我们实现这个比较器
have the correct length, what we do is
implement our own comparator. And it
它总是花相同的时间比较两个字符串。特别地
always takes the same amount of time to
compare the two strings. So in particular,
这里使用了Python里的zip函数
this uses the zip function in Python,
which will, essentially, if you are giving
给了两个16字节的字符串，它会生成16对
it two sixteen byte strings. It will
create sixteen pairs. Of bytes. So it'll
它会产生一个16个元素的列表，每个元素是一对字节
just create a, a list of sixteen elements,
where each element is a pair of bytes. One
一个取自左边，另一个取自右边。当你循环时
taken from the left and one taken from the
right. And then you loop, you know, you
循环这个列表时，计算第一对的异或
loop through this list of pairs. You
compute the XOR of the first pair, and the
然后取或作为结果；再计算第二对的异或
OR into the result. Then you
compute the XOR of the second pair, and
然后取或作为结果。大家注意到，如果这个循环里的任何一处
you OR that into the result. And
you note that, if at any point in this
两个字节正好不一样，那么它们的异或不为0
loop, two bytes happen to be not equal,
then the XOR will evaluate to something
所以当我们取异或结果的或时
that's non zero. And therefore, when we
OR'ed it into the result. The result
结果也就是在计数0，在比较的最后我们会返回假值
will also be counting on zero, and then
we'll return false, at the end of the
所以这里的比较器总是花同样长的时间
comparison. So the point here is that now
the comparator always takes the same
即使它在第三个字节处找到了不同
amount of time. Even if it finds
difference in byte number three, it will
它也会继续运行直到最后
continue running down the both strings
until the very end. And only then will it
然后才返回结果。现在计时攻击被认为是不可能了
return the results. So now the timing
attack supposedly is impossible. However,
但这样做也很有问题，因为编译器可能会帮倒忙
this can be quite problematic, because
compilers tried to be too helpful here. So
一个优化的编译器可能看到这份代码后说
an optimized compiler might look at this
code and say, hey, wait a minute. I can
等一下，我们可以优化这份代码，让这个愚蠢的循环
一旦发现不匹配的字节就结束
actually improve this code by making the
fool loop end as soon as an incompatible
因此一个优化的编译器可能是你的
set of bytes is discovered. And so, an
optimizing compiler could be your, kind
阿喀琉斯的脚后跟，当需要程序运行时间相同时。
of, Achilles heel when it comes to making
programs always take the same amount of
(阿喀琉斯的脚后跟：弱点的意思，见希腊神话)
另一个不一样的防御并不是被广泛实现的
time. And so a different defense, which is
not as widely implemented, is to try and
这种攻击试图把字符串的比较对攻击者隐藏起来
hide from the adversary, what strings are
actually being compared. So let me show
我来告诉大家什么意思。这里有我们的验证算法
you what I mean by that. So again, here we
have our verification algorithm. So it
它取密钥、信息和一个攻击者提供的候选MAC作为输入
takes as inputs, a key, a message, and a
candidate's MAC from the adversary. And
然后，我们进行比较，首先计算信息的正确MAC
then, the way we do the comparison is we
first of all, compute the correct MAC on
但然后不直接比较MAC和攻击者的签名
the message. But then instead of directly
comparing the MAC and the signature
我们再取一次哈希值
bytes adversary, what we're gonna do
is we're gonna hash one more time. So we
我们计算MAC的哈希值，我们计算签名的哈希值
compute a hash here of the MAC. We compute
a hash of the signature bytes. Of course,
当然，如果这两个是一样的，那它们的哈希也是一样的
if these two happen to be the same, then
the resulting HMACs will also be the
所以这个比较会成功
same, so the comparison will actually
succeed. But the point is now, if sig
如果签名和MAC的第一个字节一样，
先不管其他字节的情况
bytes happen to equal MAC on the first
byte, but not on the remaining bytes.
我们再算一次哈希，很有可能这两个
Then, when we do this additional hash
layer, it's likely that the two resulting
得到的值是完全不一样的。因此，逐字节的比较器
values are completely different. And as a
result, the byte by byte comparator will
会在第一轮就完成输出。这里攻击者将无法知道
just output on the first iteration. The
point here is that the adversary doesn't
到底在比较什么字符串。因此
actually know what strings are being
compared. And as a result, he can't
他不能像我们之前讨论的那样实施计时攻击
mount a timing attack that we
discussed earlier. Okay, so this is
这就是另一种防御。至少现在，你不用听优化的编译器的摆布了
another defense. At least now, you're not
at the mercy of an optimizing compiler.
这里主要的教训是，即使是专家
The main lesson from all of this is that
you realize that people who even are
在实现密码库时，也会犯这种错误
experts at implementing cryptolibraries,
get this stuff wrong. And the right code
能很好工作的代码，对计时攻击来说也是脆弱的
that works perfectly fine and yet is
completely vulnerable to a timing attack
这就让整个系统的安全性功亏一篑。
然后，这里的教训是
that completely undo all security of the
system. So the lesson here is of course
大家不应该自己发明密码
you should not be inventing your own
crypto but you shouldn't even be
甚至不应该自己实现密码，因为极有可能
你的实现对旁道攻击是脆弱的
implementing your own crypto because most
likely it'll be vulnerable to the side
请使用标准库，比如OpenSSL
channel attacks. Just use a standard
library like OpenSSL. Keyczar is actually a
Keyczar也是很好的密码库，可以降低对这些攻击
fine library to use that would reduce the
chances that you're vulnerable to these
脆弱的可能性
types of attacks.